Finding Aid for the Alfred Edwin Longueil papers LSC.1489
UCLA Library Special Collections
Alfred Edwin Longueil papers
1962-1965
UCLA Library Special Collections
Longueil, Alfred Edwin
LSC.1489
14.5 linear feet (19 boxes)
The materials consist of lecture transcripts and audio reels by UCLA Professor Alfred E. Longueil, for five different classes: Chaucer, History of English Poetry (122a), History of English Poetry (122b), Functions of Literary Criticism (201), and Romanticism (224).
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Deposited by UCLA English Department, probably 1982.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942333263606533
Biography
Alfred Edwin Longueil was born on April 3, 1894 in Dartmouth, Nova Scotia, Canada, and received his B.A. from Boston University and his M.A. and Ph.D. from Harvard University. He was named assistant professor of English at UCLA in1922, and became a full professor in 1947. He served as chair of the English department from 1936-45, and was known for his lectures on Chaucer. He was awarded the Distinguished Teaching Award and served on various committees, including the Executive Committee of the College of Applied Arts. He founded a scholarship for undergraduate women in the name of his deceased wife, Deborah King Longueil, and also endowed several graduate fellowships for study in English literature, before passing away on October 18, 1983.
Scope and Content
The materials consist of lecture transcripts and audio reels by UCLA Professor Alfred E. Longueil, for five different classes: Chaucer, History of English Poetry (122a), History of English Poetry (122b), Functions of Literary Criticism (201), and Romanticism (224). Some of the lecture transcripts for the Chaucer course are accompanied by tape recordings of the lectures, with multiple drafts included for many of the lectures. For the other courses, the lectures are only available as audio tape recordings.
Organization and Arrangement
The lectures are grouped by course, and within those groupings, are organized chronologically as well as by the numbering of the individual lectures.
Audiotapes.; Literature teachers -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Chaucer, Geoffrey; Longueil, Alfred Edwin--Archives.; University of California, Los Angeles. Department of English--Faculty -- Archives
- Preliminaries, including Versification and Language, 1963 February 4 - 13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  "Chaucer #1: Preliminaries-Tolerably Dull" (Print History, Reception, and Editorial Challenges); "Chaucer #2: Chaucer's Verse and Language"
  "Chaucer #3: More Preliminaries: Chaucer's Language" (Orthography, Phonology, Morphology)
  "Chaucer #4: Still Preliminary--Chaucer's Idiom"
  "Chaucer #5: Chaucer's Grammar" (Grammatical Gender, Parts of Speech, etc.)
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Chaucer Lectures 1 and 2, 1963 February 4 - 6; 5 inch reel audiotapes and smaller magnetic recording tapes labeled: inchDeJur Gruindig for exclusive use with Stenorette Dictating and Transcribing Machines--45min. inch (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Audio reels containing Chaucer Lectures #1 and 2
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Chaucer Lectures 3 and 4, 1963 February 8 -11; 5 inch reel audiotape (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Audio reels containing Chaucer Lectures 3 and 4
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Lectures 5 and 6, 1963 February 13 -15; 5 inch reel audiotape (Box 1, Folder 4)
  (3) Reels containg Lectures 5 and 6
- Knight's Tale #1, 1963 February 15 -25 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  "Chaucer #6: Chaucer's Grammar, continued" (Includes lengthy discussion of Knight's Tale)
  "Chaucer #7:"The Knight's Tale" (DRAFT)
  "Chaucer #8: Knight's Tale and the medieval storytelling technique"
  "Chaucer #9: The Knight's Tale"
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Chaucer Lectures 7 and 8, 1963 Feb 18 - 20; 5 inch reel audiotape (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Audio Reels of Lectures 7 and 8
- Knight's Tale #2 transcripts, 1963 February 27 -March 11 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  "Chaucer #10: The Knight's Tale"
  "Chaucer #11: The Knight's Tale, Book II"
  "Chaucer #12: The Knight's Tale, Book III"
  "Chaucer #13: The Knight's Tale, Book IV"
  "Chaucer #14: The Knight's Tale Concluded--The Romance"
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Chaucer Lectures 9 - 12, 1963 February 25-27; 1963 March 1-4; 3 1/4 inch and 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Knight's tale
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Chaucer Lectures 13 and 14, 1963 March 6 - 8; 3 1/4 inch and 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Knight's Tale
- Book of the Duchess transcripts, 1963 March 11 - 15 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  "Chaucer #15: The Book of the Duchess"
  "Chaucer #16: The Book of the Duchess"
  "Chaucer #17: Courtly Love"
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Chaucer Lectures 15 and 16, 1963 March 11-13; 3 1/4 inch and 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Book of the Duchess
- House of Fame transcripts, 1963 March 18 - 25 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  "Chaucer #18: The House of Fame, Book 1"
  "Chaucer #19: The House of Fame, Book II"
  "Chaucer #20: The House of Fame, Book III"
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordingsof Chaucer Lectures 17 and 18, 1963 March 15-18; 3 1/4 inch and 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Courtly Love and House of Fame
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Chaucer Lectures 19 and 20, 1963 March 20 - 25; 3 1/4 inch and 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 3, Folder 6)
  House of Fame
- Anelinda and Arcite and Parliament of Fowls transcripts, 1963 March 27 - April 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  "Chaucer #21: Anelida and Arcite and Parliament of Fowls"
  "Chaucer #22: Parliament of Fowls, cont'd"
  "Chaucer #23: Italian Influences on Chaucer"
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Chaucer Lectures 21 and 22, 1963 March 27 - 29; 3 1/4 inch and 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Parliament of Fowls
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Lectures 23 - 24, 1963 April 1 - 3; 3 1/4 inch and 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Italian Influences on Chaucer and Troilus and Cressida
- Troilus and Criseyde transcripts, 1963 April 3 - 19 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  "Chaucer #24, #25, #26, #27 (Draft only), and #28 (Draft only): "Troilus and Criseyde and Legend of Good Women"
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Chaucer Lectures 25 and 26, 1963 April 5 -15; 3 1/4 inch and 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Troilus and Cressida
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Chaucer Lectures 27 and 28, 1963 April 17- 19; 3 1/4 inch and 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Lecture 27: "Troilus and Creside (fin) and Legend of Good Women"
  Lecture 28: "Canterbury Tales"
- Mediaeval Background transcripts, 1963 April 22 -24 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  "Chaucher #29: The Mediaeval Background, 300-1400"
  "Chaucer #30: The Mediaeval Background, cont."
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Chaucer Lectures 29 and 30, 1963 April 22 -24; 3 1/4 inch and 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Chaucer Lectures 31 and 32, 1963 April 26 - 29; 3 1/4 inch and 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 5, Folder 5)
- General Prologue transcripts, 1963 April 29 - May 03 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  Lectures #31 (draft only), 32, 33, 34: General Prologue
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Chaucer Lectures 33 and 34, 1963 May 1 - 3; 3 1/4 inch and 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Lectures 35 and 36, 1963 May 6 - 8; 3 1/4 inch and 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Lectures on various individual tales, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  Lecture 35: "Squire's Tale, Monk's Tale, Second Nun's Tale"
  Lecture 36: "Clerk's Tale, Shipman's Tale, Friar's Tale"
  Lecture 37: "Friar's Tale, Franklin's Tale"
  Lecture 38: "Franklin's Tale, The Tale of Sir Thopas"
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Chaucer Lectures 37 and 38, 1963 May 10 - 13; 3 1/4 inch and 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Nun's Priest's Tale transcript, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  Lecture 39: "Nun's Priest's Tale"
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Chaucer Lectures 39 and 40, 1963 May 15 - 17; 3 1/4 inch and 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 7, Folder 2)
  Lecture 40, for which we do not have a transcript, is labeled on the tape as "Pardoner's Tale"
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Lectures 41 and 42, 1963 May 20 - 22; 3 1/4 inch and 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 7, Folder 3)
  These tapes do not have transcripts:
  Lecture # 41: "Wife of Bath's Tale"
  Lecture #42: "Canon's Yeoman's Tale"
  Lecture #43: "Links to Canterbury Tales"
- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Chaucer Lecture 43, 1963 May 24; 3 1/4 inch and 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 7, Folder 4)
  These tapes do not have transcripts :Lecture #43: "Links to Canterbury Tales"
- History of English Poetry - English 122a - Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Lectures 1 - 41, 1964 September 21 - Nov 2; 3 1/4 inch reel audiotape (Box 8)
  Lecture 1: Introduction
  Lecture 2: Introduction
  Lecture 3: Early Anglo-Saxon Poetry
  Lecture 4: Beowulf
  Lecture 5: Epic poetry and its Techniques, Style [note: "This tape is defective. Add the notes"; no accompanying transcript]
  Lecture 6: Religious Poetry of Anglo-Saxons; [note: "This tape is defective. And the notes must be added]
  Lecture 7: Normal Conquest
  Lecture 8: Background of Middle English Poetry ["Tape is defective. Add notes"]
  Lecture 9: Background of Middle English Poetry Cont. ["Tape is defective. Add notes"]
  Lecture 10: Meter ["1/2 of the lesson; faster speed 3 and 3/4]
  Lecture 11: Romances
  Lecture 12: History of the English Lyric"
  Lecture 13: History of the English Lyric II
  Lecture 14: The 4 Great Middle English Poets
  Lecture 15: Chaucer
  Lecture 16: Chaucer and his Craft
  Lecture 17: Canterbury Tales: Prologue
  Lecture 18: Chaucer: 3 Tales
  Lecture 19: Chaucer's Nun's Priest's Tale
  Lecture 20: Late Medieval Poets
  Lecture 21: Late Medieval Scotish Poets and John Skelton and Intro to the Ballad
  Lecture 22: Ballads
  Lecture 23: Ballads and Popular Lyric
  Lecture 24: Renaisance History
  Lecture 25: Renaissance History of Art and Literature
  Lecture 26: Wyatt and Surrey
  Lecture 27: Wyatt and Surrey, Miscellanies
  Lecture 28: Sonnet Sequences Sidney, Shakespeare
  Lecture 29: Elizabethan Songs
  Lecture 30: Long lyrics and Pastorals of Elizabethan Period, particularly Spenser
  Lecture 31: Continuation of long lyrics and pastoral tradition in Elizabetha Age
  Lecture 32: Faerie Queen I
  Lecture 33: Faerie Queen II
  Lecture 33: Faerie Queen III, Literary Criticism of Eliz. Age
  Lecture 34: Sidney's Defense of Poetry and Subsequent Criticism
  Lecture 35: King Lear
  Lecture 36: Lear II and Raleigh
  Lecture 37: Jonson and Donne
  Lecture 38: Donne
  Lecture 39: Donne II
  Lecture 40: Donne III--Movement to the 17th Century
  Lecture 41: 17th Atmosphere and Reasons for that Atmosphere
- English 201 - Functions of literary criticism - Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Lectures 1-10, 1962 September 17 - October 9; 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 9)
- English 201 - Functions of literary criticism - Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Lectures 9 - 19, 1962 October 5 - 29; 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 10)
- English 201 - Functions of literary criticism - Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Lectures 20 - 28, 1962 October 31 - November 21; 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 11)
- English 201 - Functions of literary criticism - Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Lectures 29 - 38, 1962 November 21 - 1963 January 2; 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 12)
- Eng 201- Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Lec. 37- 42 and Eng. 122B - Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Lec. 42 - 49, 1962 December 14 - 1963 January 11 and 1965 February 8 - 29; 3 inch and 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 13)
  Lecture topics for English 122B:
  Lecture 42: 17th Century Lyricists
  Lecture 43: Lovelace, Suckling, Herbert; Lecture 44: 17th [century] religious lyric poetry
  Lecture 45: Herrick, Waller, Cowley
  Lecture 46: Narrative poetry of 17th
  Lecture 47: Milton: Early Minor Poems
  Lecture 48: Milton: Horton Period and Retirement Period
  Lecture 49: Milton: Style in P.L.)
- English 122B - History of English Poetry - Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Lectures 50 - 69, 1965 March 3 - April 26; 3 inch reel audiotape (Box 14)
  Lecture topics:
  Lecture 50: Milton: P.L.
  Lecture 51: Milton: R.R. and Samson, Approach of the 18th C
  Lecture 52: Dryden I
  Lecture 53: Dryden II
  Lecture 54: Change within 18th C
  Lecture 55: Pope I--Essays
  Lecture 56: Pope II--Fictional Writing
  Lecture 57: Romantic Evolution
  Lecture 58: Romantics: Collins and Gray
  Lecture 59: Goldsmith, Cowper, Burns
  Lecture 60: Burns and Blake
  Lecture 61: Blake--Romantic changes
  Lecture 62: 19th Century--Scott and Coleridge
  Lecture 63: Coleridge and Wordsworth
  Lecture 64: Wordsworth
  Lecture 65: Wordsworth
  Lecture 66: Keats
  Lecture 67: Shelley
  Lecture 68: Byron
  Lecture 69: Byron and Victorian Age
- English 122B - History of English Poetry - Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Lectures 70-83, 1965 April 28 - May 28; 3 inch reel audiotape (Box 15)
  Lecture 70: Pre-Raphaelites
  Lecture 71: Swinburne, Clough, Arnold
  Lecture 72: Meredith, Thomson
  Lecture 73: Tennyson
  Lecture 74: Tennyson and Browning
  Lecture 75: Browning
  Lecture 76: Victorian Light verse and aesthetic poets
  Lecture 77: Hardy, Houseman
  Lecture 78: Bridges, Hopkins
  Lecture 79: Yeats
  Lecture 80: Kipling, Yeats, 20th C
  Lecture 81: Early 20th Century and Impressionism
  Lecture 82: Expressionism--Sitwel and Eliot
  Lecture 83: Eliot, Thomas, Auden
- English 224 - Romanticism - Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Lectures 1 - 10, 1962 September 19 - October 10; 5 inch reel audiotape (Box 16)
- English 224 - Romanticism - Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Lectures 9 - 19, 1962 October 8 - 31; 5 inch reel audiotape (Box 17)
- English 224 - Romanticism - Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Lectures 19 - 28, 1962 October 31 - November 26; 5 inch reel audiotape (Box 18)
- English 224 - Romanticism - Audio reel magnetic tape recordings of Lectures 29 - 40, 1962 November 28 - 1963 January 9; 3 inch and 5 inch reel audiotapes (Box 19)
  Also includes an unnumbered, undated audio reel magnetic tape recording of "Final lecture"